Hey everyone!
みんな、こんにちは！
So have you ever felt a little nervous starting a conversation with someone new?
新しい人と会話を始めるとき、緊張したことはありますか？
You know that moment where you're like, what do I even say?
何を言えばいいのか、迷う瞬間ですよね。
Well today we're going to unlock a secret to making new friends and just having awesome
今日は、新しい友達を作る秘訣をお教えします。
chats.
素晴らしい会話を楽しむために。
It's a superpower and it's hidden in two super simple words, do and does.
それはスーパーパワーで、2つのシンプルな言葉、doとdoesに隠れています。
Think of this as your guide to becoming a total conversation master.
これを会話の達人になるためのガイドと考えてください。
Let's get started. So let's try it out.
さあ、始めましょう。試してみましょう。
I'll ask you a question right now, okay? Do you like video games?
今、質問しますね。ビデオゲームは好きですか？
Go ahead, think about your answer.
考えてみてください。
Did you think, yes I do, or maybe no I don't? See?
「はい、好きです」とか「いいえ、好きじゃない」と思いましたか？
You're already using this conversation superpower and you probably didn't even realize it.
もうこの会話のスーパーパワーを使っていますよ、気づいていなかったかもしれませんが。
Now, let's break down how to use this power to learn about pretty much anyone.
では、この力を使って誰についてでも学ぶ方法を見ていきましょう。
You know, every great conversation, every friendship, it all starts with one simple thing, a question.
素晴らしい会話や友情は、すべて一つのシンプルなこと、質問から始まります。
It's seriously the easiest way to show you're interested in someone.
相手に興味を示す最も簡単な方法です。
So let's begin our friendship quest right now.
さあ、友情の冒険を始めましょう。
And here's the golden rule for our mission, the most important part.
私たちのミッションの黄金ルール、最も重要な部分です。
The first step is always to ask about the other person.
最初のステップは、常に相手について尋ねることです。
People love to talk about what they like and what they do.
人は自分の好きなことやしていることについて話すのが好きです。
It's the absolute fastest way to find something
共通点を見つける最も早い方法です。
you both have in common.
さて、友情の冒険のレベル1です。
All right, it's time for level one of our friendship quest.
最も重要な質問から始めましょう。
We're kicking things off with the most important question of all,
実際に話している相手について尋ねることです。
asking about the person you're actually talking to.
ここで「do you」をマスターします。
This is where we master the classic, do you.
シンプルで直接的、そして毎回効果があります。
It's simple, it's direct, and trust me, it works every single time.
例を使いましょう。誰かに「寿司は好きですか？」と聞いてみてください。
Let's use an example. So imagine you ask someone, do you like sushi?
もし好きなら「はい、好きです」と言います。
If they do, they'll say, yes, I do, pretty simple.
好きじゃなければ「いいえ、好きじゃない」と言います。
If they don't, they'll say, no, I don't.
答えが質問と同じ言葉を使っているのがわかりますか？
See how the answer uses the same word you started the question with?
まるで完璧なエコーのようです。「do」が「do」または「don't」を引き出します。
It's like a perfect little echo, do gets you do or don't.
さて、ここで面白いのは「do not」と「don't」の違いです。
Okay, now what's really interesting here is the difference between do not and
「いいえ、好きではありません」は正しいですが、少し堅苦しいですよね。
don't. I mean, no, I do not is totally correct,
エッセイを書いているような感じです。
but it sounds a bit formal, right?
友達と話しているときは、
Kind of like you're writing an essay.
特にアメリカでは、ほとんど「いいえ、好きじゃない」と言います。
you're almost always gonna hear the contraction, no, I don't.
それは早くて、カジュアルで、
It's just quicker, way more casual,
自然に聞こえます。
and it'll make you sound supernatural.
さて、あなたは「あなたについて尋ねる」ことを完全にマスターしました。
Okay, so you've totally mastered asking about you.
次はレベル2です。
It's time for level two.
ここから会話が本当に面白くなります。
This is where conversations get really interesting,
他の人について尋ねることができます。
because you can start asking about other people,
友達の兄弟や好きな先生など、誰でも。
like your friend's brother or their favorite teacher, anyone.
そのために新しい魔法の言葉が必要です、「does」です。
And for that, we need a new magic word, does.
では、シンプルな文から始めましょう。「彼は上手に歌います」。
So let's start with a really simple statement. He sings well.
「s」が最後についているのがわかりますか？その「s」が鍵です。
See that little S on the end of sings? That S is the key.
これは、1人の他の人、彼または彼女について話していることを示しています。
It's a signal that we're talking about
さあ、質問に変えますよ。
just one other person, a he or a she.
でも、ここでよくある間違いに注意してください。
Now get ready because we're about to flip this into a question.
多くの人が「彼は上手に歌いますか？」と言うかもしれません。
But watch out, here's a super common mistake.
一見論理的に思えますが、英語ではこれは完全に間違いです。
A lot of people might say, does he sings well?
正しい質問の仕方に直さなければなりません。
It kind of seems logical, right? But in English, this is a total trap.
秘密は、「彼は上手に歌いますか？」です。では、「s」はどこに行ったのでしょう？
We've gotta fix this to ask the question the right way.
「does」をスーパーヒーローだと考えてください。
And here is the secret. Does he sing well? So where did the S go?
「does」が飛んできて、動詞「sing」の「s」をつかみます。
Okay, think of does as a superhero.
だから「does」が「s」を持っているので、
It flies in and it grabs the S from the verb sing.
動詞「sing」は元のシンプルな形に戻ります。
So since does is now carrying the S,
このルールを覚えておいてください。「does」が現れるとき、
the next verb never has an S.
次の動詞には絶対にSがつかない。
You know, to make this even easier to remember,
覚えやすくするために、
let's think of it as two different teams.
2つのチームに分けて考えよう。
On the do team, we've got I, you, we, and they.
「do」チームには、I、you、we、theyがいる。
For anyone on that team, you use do.
このチームの誰かにはdoを使う。
But on the does team, we have the special players, he, she, and it.
「does」チームには、特別なメンバーのhe、she、itがいる。
And this also includes any single person's name, like John or Emily.
また、JohnやEmilyのような個人名も含まれる。
For anyone on this team, you always, always use does.
このチームの誰かには、必ずdoesを使う。
And this shows a great pro tip for sounding like a native speaker.
これはネイティブのように聞こえるためのコツだ。
When you ask a question like, does John have a bike?
例えば、「Johnは自転車を持っていますか？」と聞くと、
The most natural answer isn't yes, John does.
自然な答えは「はい、彼は持っています」ではなく、
Instead, you swap the name for the pronoun. Yes, he does.
「はい、彼は持っています」と代名詞に変える。
It's such a small change,
小さな変化だけど、
but it makes a huge difference in how natural you sound.
自然さに大きな違いをもたらす。
Okay, let's broaden our conversation skills a little more.
さて、会話スキルをさらに広げよう。
What if you wanna ask about a whole group of people,
友達の家族や好きなバンドについて聞きたいときは、
like your friend's family or your favorite band?
「do」を使って「they」について尋ねる。
Well, this is where we bring back our old friend,
そして、最も良い点は、
Do, to ask about they. And the best part?
パターンは「do」と全く同じで、とても簡単。
The pattern is exactly the same as DU. It's super, super easy.
「彼らは上手に歌いますか？」と聞けば、
If you ask, do they sing well?
答えは「はい、彼らは歌います」または「いいえ、歌いません」。
The answer is simply, yes they do, or no they don't.
スポーツチームや好きな歌手について聞くのにぴったり。
Perfect for asking about a sports team
もう一つのヒント。
or, you know, your favorite singers. And here's another quick tip.
2人以上の名前を挙げて話すときは、
If you're talking about two or more people by name,
「JohnとPaulはギターを弾きますか？」のように。
like in the question, do John and Paul play the guitar?
答えでは、その名前は「they」になる。
In your answer, those names just become they.
だから「はい、彼らは弾きます」と言う。
So you'd say, yes, they do.
これは2人以上の組み合わせに使える。
This works for any combo of two or more people. Simple as that.
シンプルだね。
Okay, you've learned all the skills.
さて、すべてのスキルを学んだ。
So now it's time to put them to the test with a fun little challenge.
次は楽しいチャレンジで試してみよう。
We're gonna become detectives on a mission
私たちは探偵になって、
to uncover some secrets about a girl named Jennifer.
Jenniferという女の子の秘密を探る。
Let's see if we can use our do and does skills to find the facts.
doとdoesのスキルを使って事実を見つけよう。
Okay, detectives, here is your mission file.
探偵たち、こちらがあなたのミッションファイル。
I'm gonna give you a quick moment
Jenniferについての段落を
to read this paragraph about Jennifer.
少し読んでみて。
All the clues you need are hidden right inside. Ready?
必要な手がかりはすべてその中に隠れている。準備はいい？
All right, here come the questions. All right, first question.
では、質問に行こう。最初の質問。
Look at the text, does Jennifer go to junior high school?
テキストを見て、Jenniferは中学校に通っていますか？
Find the answer, got it? And the answer is, yes, she does.
答えを見つけた？答えは「はい、彼女は通っています」。
The text says, I'm in junior high school. Awesome start, detectives.
テキストには「私は中学校にいます」と書いてある。素晴らしいスタートだ、探偵たち。
Okay, question two, do her parents eat meat?
さて、質問2、彼女の両親は肉を食べますか？
Look carefully, the text says, my parents don't eat meat.
よく見て、テキストには「私の両親は肉を食べません」とある。
So the answer is, no, they don't. You're on a roll.
だから答えは「いいえ、彼らは食べません」。いい調子だ。
Question three, does she like sushi? This one's a tasty clue.
質問3、彼女は寿司が好きですか？これはおいしい手がかり。
She says, I also enjoy sushi. So that's a big yes, she does.
彼女は「私も寿司が好きです」と言っている。だから大きな「はい、彼女は好き」です。
All right, final question. Do her parents go to Japanese restaurants?
さて、最後の質問。彼女の両親は日本のレストランに行きますか？
The last sentence says, we often go.
最後の文には「私たちはよく行きます」と書いてある。
And that we includes her and their parents.
その「私たち」には彼女と両親が含まれる。
So the answer is, yes they do.
だから答えは「はい、彼らは行きます」。
Mission complete, you totally cracked the case. Fantastic work.
ミッション完了、あなたは完全に事件を解決した。素晴らしい仕事だ。
You've officially graduated from our friendship quest.
あなたは友情のクエストを正式に卒業した。
And to make sure you never forget your new superpowers,
新しいスーパーパワーを忘れないように、
I've put everything together on one final cheat sheet.
最後のチートシートをまとめた。
This is your master key for starting any conversation.
これは会話を始めるためのマスターキー。
This simple little table is your master key.
このシンプルな表があなたのマスターキー。
For you and they, you're on the do team.
「you」と「they」はdoチーム。
For he and she, you're on the does team.
「he」と「she」はdoesチーム。
And the golden rule, the most important part,
そして黄金のルール、最も重要な部分、
is right there at the bottom. After do or does, the verb is always
文の最後にあります。doやdoesの後は、動詞は常に
in its original simple form, no extra S.
原形のままで、余分なSは付きません。
That is the number one thing to remember.
これが最も重要なポイントです。
So we've unlocked the secret.
これで秘密が解けました。
You now have the keys to start a conversation with anyone, anywhere.
あなたは今、誰とでもどこでも会話を始めるための鍵を手に入れました。
All it takes is one simple question.
必要なのは、たった一つのシンプルな質問です。
So my final question to you is this.
では、最後の質問です。
What question will you ask someone today?
今日は誰にどんな質問をしますか？
Go out there and start a conversation. Thanks for tuning in.
外に出て会話を始めましょう。ご視聴ありがとうございました。